A Finding Aid to the Aldro T. Hibbard Papers, 1914-1971, in the Archives of American Art
Archives of American Art
Aldro T. Hibbard papers
1914-1971
Archives of American Art
Hibbard, A. T. (Aldro Thompson) (1886-1972)
AAA.hibbaldr
Archival Resource Key
1.7 Linear feet
The papers of landscape painter Aldro T. Hibbard measure 1.7 linear feet and date from 1914 to 1971. The papers document his career as a painter through correspondence; diaries, notes and other writings; awards, discussions, and other professional activity; clippings, exhibition catalogs, and other printed material; and personal sound recordings.
Conditions Governing Access
This collection is open for research. Access to original papers requires an appointment and is limited to the Archives' Washington, D.C. Research Center. Researchers interested in accessing audiovisual recordings in this collection must use access copies. Contact References Services for more information.
Scope and Contents
The papers of landscape painter Aldro T. Hibbard measure 1.7 linear feet and date from 1914 to 1971. The papers document his career as a painter through correspondence; diaries, notes and other writings; awards, discussions, and other professional activity files; clippings, exhibition catalogs, and other printed material; and personal sound recordings.
Correspondence includes letters to his wife, Winifred, fan letters, and letters to friends and art organizations. Writings include notes, a notebook, a diary of his travels through Europe in 1914, and a diary from 1962. Professional material includes awards, an audio reel lecture delivered to the Rockport Art Association, one motion picture film, photographs of Hibbard and his students, and a biographical statement. Printed material includes newspaper clippings, exhibition announcements and catalogs, and material related to the Hibbard School of Painting. Sound Recordings consist of 17 wire recordings. The recordings are mostly unlabeled and primarily personal in nature, but some contain lectures and sales records.
Existence and Location of Copies
Portions of the collection are available on 35mm microfilm reels 373-374 and 2163 at Archives of American Art offices and through interlibrary loan. Researchers should note that the container inventory does not reflect the arrangement of the collection on microfilm.
Biographical / Historical
Aldro T. Hibbard (1886-1972) was an American landscape painter who worked primarily in oil. He studied at the Massachusetts College of Art and Design and later at the Museum of Fine Arts, Boston. Hibbard assisted in founding the Rockport Art Association and served as its president for 20 years. Hibbard also created and taught at the Hibbard School of Painting in Rockport, Massachusetts.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The Aldro Hibbard papers were donated 1977 and 1979 by Winifred Hibbard, the widow of Aldro T. Hibbard.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged into five series.
Series 1: Correspondence, 1922-1971 (0.5 linear feet; Box 1)
Series 2: Writings, circa 1914-1962 (0.1 linear feet; Box 1)
Series 3: Professional Activity Files, 1927-1971 (0.2 linear feet; Box 1, FC 4)
Series 4: Printed Material, 1933-1970 (0.5 linear feet; Boxes 1-2)
Series 5: Sound Recordings, circa 1950 (0.4 linear feet; Boxes 2-3)
Sound recordings; Painters -- Massachusetts -- Rockport; Diaries
- Correspondence, 1922-1971; Series 1; Archival Resource Key; 0.5 Linear feet Box 1
  Scope and Contents
  Correspondence includes letters to his wife, Winifred, fan letters, and letters to friends and art organizations.
  - Winifred Hibbard, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 1-2)
  - Correspondence, 1922-1923; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, 1924; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 4-11)
  - Correspondence, 1925; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 12-16)
  - Correspondence, 1926; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 17-18)
  - Correspondence, 1927; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Correspondence, 1928; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Correspondence, 1930-1933; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Correspondence, 1934-1938; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Correspondence, 1943-1971; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 23-24)
  - Fan Letters, 1959-1961; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 25)
- Writings, circa 1914-1962; Series 2; Archival Resource Key; 0.1 Linear feet Box 1
  Writings include notes, a notebook, a diary of Hibbard's travels through Europe in 1914, and a diary from 1962.
  - Diary, 1962; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Diary of Europe, circa 1914; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Notebook, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Miscellaneous, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 29)
- Professional Activity Files, 1927-1971; Series 3; Archival Resource Key; 0.2 Linear feet Box 1, FC 4
  Professional material includes awards, an audio reel lecture delivered to the Rockport Art Association, one motion picture film, photographs of Hibbard and his students, and a biographical statement.
  - Awards, 1958-1971; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Hibbard School of Painting, 1927-1948; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - "Importance of Discussion to Art Students" Lecture, 1961 August 24; Archival Resource Key; 1 Sound tape reel (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - "Memory of an Old Friend", undated; Archival Resource Key; 1 Motion picture film 8 mm (Item FC 4)
    Footage of a man and woman on a balcony, dark exposure of a man, a man, and a chimpanzee.
  - Miscellaneous Photos, circa 1955; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Miscellaneous, 1940-1963; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 34)
- Printed Material, 1933-1970; Series 4; Archival Resource Key; 0.5 Linear feet Boxes 1-2
  Printed material includes newspaper clippings, exhibition announcements and catalogs, and material related to the Hibbard School of Painting.
  - Clippings, 1933-1970; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 35-39)
  - Exhibition Announcements and Catalogs, 1948-1967; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Hibbard School of Painting, 1942-1952; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Miscellaneous, 1945-1970; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 3)
- Sound Recordings, circa 1950; Series 5; Archival Resource Key; 0.4 Linear feet Boxes 2-3
  Sound Recordings consist of 17 wired recordings. The recordings are mostly unlabeled and primarily personal in nature containing family gatherings and baseball games, but some contain lectures and sales records.
  - Personal Recordings, circa 1950; Archival Resource Key; 12 Sound wire reels (Box 2, Folder 4-6)
  - Personal Recordings, circa 1950; Archival Resource Key; 5 Sound wire reels (Box 3, Folder 1-2)